Finding Aid for the Yasui Family Papers, 1907-1946 LSC.2010.20
UCLA Library Special Collections
Yasui Family papers
1907-1946
UCLA Library Special Collections
Yasui family
LSC.2010.20
3.5 Linear Feet (5 boxes, 2 flat boxes)
Satosuke Yasui was born in 1881 in Hiroshima Prefecture. He arrived in Hawaii in 1907, where he was a newspaperman, Japanese language school principal and teacher, and publisher and editor of the Maui Shimbun. He also served as an officer of the Japanese Association of Maui. The collection consists of personal papers, diaries, correspondence, instructional materials, informational publications, sound recordings, artwork, and photographs related to the Yasui family. The collection also includes papers related to the Japanese Association of Wailuku, Hawaii, and a notebook of sermon memos kept by Jodo Shinshu Buddhist priest, Taksuhiko Matsuda, at Tule Lake. Some materials in this collection are in Japanese.
Restrictions on Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of the Japanese American Research Project of the Japanese American Citizens League, 1973.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9942340433606533
Biography
Satosuke Yasui was born in 1881 in the Hiroshima Prefecture, Japan. He graduated from Hiroshima Normal School and arrived in Hawaii in 1907. He was a newspaperman and Japanese language school principal and teacher. He was also publisher and editor of the Maui Shimbun (1920-41). He served as an officer of the Japanese Association of Maui.
Scope and Content
Collection consists of personal papers, diaries, correspondence, instructional materials, informational publications, sound recordings, artwork, and photographs related to the Yasui family. Personal papers consist of Satosuke Yasui's 18 notebook diaries (1910-41), correspondence, and miscellaneous items such as practice sheets of calligraphy, instructional materials, Japanese sound recordings, artwork, and a photo album. The collection also includes papers related to the Japanese Assn. of Wailuku, Hawaii, a small amount of articles published in the Maui Shimbun, and a notebook of sermon memos kept by Jodo Shinshu Buddhist priest Taksuhiko Matsuda, at Tule Lake.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Artwork
Diaries
Miscellaneous
Organizational files
Photographs
Printed materials.
Related Material
Manzanar War Relocation Center Records (Collection 122). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Japanese American Research Project Collection of Material about Japanese in the United States (Collection 2010). Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Sound recordings.; Family papers.; Photographs.; Japanese American families -- Hawaii -- Archives.; Teachers -- Hawaii -- Archives.; Diaries.; Japanese American Research Project (University of California, Los Angeles); Yasui family; Yasui, Matsuno--Archives.; Yasui, Satosuke--Archives.
- Artwork, 1938; n.d.; 1 box (.5 linear ft.) and 1 flat box.
  Scope and Contents note
  Series consists of Japanese calligraphy, water colors, pencil sketches, and charcoal drawings.
  - Japanese calligraphy by Matsuno Yasui--29, n.d.; [29 folders.] (Box 147, Folder 1-29)
  - Pen and water color by Fujita, 1938 (Box 723, Folder 1)
  - Pencil and ink on Japanese paper [artist unknown] (Box 723, Folder 2)
  - Water color [artist unknown], n.d. (Box 723, Folder 3)
  - Water color [artist unknown], n.d. (Box 723, Folder 4)
  - Water color and oil by Iao Yasui (Box 723, Folder 5)
  - Water color by Iao Yasui, n.d. (Box 723, Folder 6)
  - Water color by Iao Yasui, n.d. (Box 723, Folder 7)
  - Water color by Iao Yasui, n.d. (Box 723, Folder 8)
  - Water color, abstract patterns, by Iao Yasui, n.d. (Box 723, Folder 9)
  - Water color, abstract patterns, by Iao Yasui, n.d. (Box 723, Folder 10)
  - Water color, people, places, things, by Iao Yasui, n.d. (Box 723, Folder 11)
  - Pencil, composition of three-dimensional patterns, by Iao Yasui, n.d. (Box 723, Folder 12)
  - Pencil sketches of still life by Iao Yasui, n.d. (Box 723, Folder 13)
  - Pencil sketches of interior by Iao Yasui, n.d. (Box 723, Folder 14)
  - Charcoal drawing by Iao Yasui, n.d. (Box 723, Folder 15)
  - Pencil and Japanese ink by Iao Yasui (Box 874, Folder 1)
  - Calligraphy mounted on paper, n.d. (Box 874, Folder 2)
- Diaries, 1911-1941; 2 boxes (1 linear ft.)
  Series consists of various diaries (sick bed, poetry, etc.). All are in Japanese.
  - Kiyoko, Yasui--Notebooks and paper pads, 1911-1915 (Box 148, Folder 1)
    In Japanese.
  - Yasui, Satosuke--Bound diaries, 1916-1917 (Box 148, Folder 2)
  - Yasui, Satosuke--Bound diaries, 1919, 1922 (Box 148, Folder 3)
  - Yasui, Satosuke--Various personal diaries, 1910-1912, 1915, 1934-1935 (Box 148, Folder 4)
  - Yasui, Satosuke--Poetry diary--Nisshi uta, 1939 January-October (Box 149, Folder 1)
    Poem composed in sick-bed. In Japanese.
  - Yasui, Satosuke--Poetry diary--Nisshi uta, 1939 November-1940 December (Box 149, Folder 2)
  - Yasui, Satosuke--Poetry diary--Nisshi uta, 1941 January-December (Box 149, Folder 3)
  - Yasui, Satosuke--Sick-bed diary--Hakuajyo tobyo nisshi, 1939 March-April (Box 149, Folder 4)
    Diaries includes the condition of his disease and diet. In Japanese.
  - Yasui, Satosuke--Sick-bed diary--Hakuajyo tobyo nisshi, 1939 May-August (Box 149, Folder 5)
- Miscellaneous, 1909-1945; 1 box (.5 linear ft.)
  Series consists of various items including a small amount of correspondence, clippings, blueprints, lecture notes, scrapbook, notebook, and phonograph records.
  - Phonograph records--School song/national anthem--Royaru Saiho Jyogakko koka [Royaru Girls School for Sewing School Song], Kimigayo hensokyoku(Jyo)[National Anthem of Japan], n.d. (Box 147, Folder 30)
    Four copies of Royaru Saiho Jyogakko koka.
  - Phonograph records--School song--Royaru Saiho Jyogakko koka [Royaru Girls School for Sewing School Song], n.d. (Box 147, Folder 31)
    78 rpm records.
  - Yasui, Satosuke--Sick-bed diary--Hakuajyo tobyo nisshi, 1939 September-1941 January (Box 149, Folder 6)
    Diaries includes the condition of his disease, diet, list of visitors. In Japanese.
  - Correspondence--to Yasui Family, 1911-1932 (Box 150, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence--From Satosuke to Matsuno (Box 150, Folder 2)
    Written instructions by Satosuke to his bride, Matsuno, explaining what to bring, how to behave, and where to stay, etc., when the latter was coming to Hawaii as a bride. In Japanese.
  - Financial papers, 1908-1916 (Box 150, Folder 3)
  - Clippings of women's magazine & sewing patterns, n.d. (Box 150, Folder 4)
  - Lecture notes from English classes, 1936 October-1937 May (Box 150, Folder 5)
  - Lecture notes from sewing classes, 1936 September-1937 March (Box 150, Folder 6)
    For Matsuno Yasui.
  - Lecture notes--various subjects (Box 150, Folder 7)
  - Draft of various plays/skits, n.d. (Box 150, Folder 8)
    "Visit flight to 50 Japanese cities, 1929", "Lazy man", "A drummer boy", "Zeppelin", "Ski tournament", "Reconstruction of Tokyo", "Aiming at the glory". In Japanese.
  - Poems, musical notes, n.d. (Box 150, Folder 9)
  - Results of a Judo tournament, n.d. (Box 150, Folder 10)
    Record book of a Judo tournament. 1 notebook, and three papers are placed in clear folder
  - Three blueprints and a photograph of memorial stones (Box 150, Folder 11)
  - Notebook--Translation of Dr. Sidney L. Gulick's article on the Sino-Japanese War by Yukihira Tsuyoshi, 1937 (Box 150, Folder 12)
  - Scrapbook--Santa Anita Assembly Center--Drawings and writings about the Santa Anita Assembly Center by Shinichi Furuya, 1942, 1945 (Box 874, Folder 3)
- Organizational files, 1911-1931; (.25 linear ft.)
  Series contains small amount of miscellaneous papers related to various organizations.
  - Appointment paper of Satosuke Yasui, 1911 May (Box 150, Folder 13)
    Appointment paper of Satosuke Yasui as principal and teacher of a Buddhist Japanese language school in Papaiko, Hawaii. In Japanese.
  - Company Daily Reports "Maui Shinbunsha nikki" [Maui Newspaper Publisher Diary], 1923 January 1-1925 February 27; 1940 May 19-October 24 (Box 151, Folder 1)
  - Japanese Association of Wailuku--Issen-kyu-hyaku-sanjyu-nendo Wairuku Nihonjin-kai jinmeihyo [Membership list of the Japanese Association of Wailuku, 1937] (Box 151, Folder 2)
  - Japanese Association of Wailuku--check book, 1918 November 25-1931 January 3 (Box 151, Folder 3)
  - Japanese Association of Wailuku--receipts, 1930 January-1931 January (Box 151, Folder 4)
  - Twenty-First Maui County Fair--List of awards in the Vegetable Section, n.d. (Box 151, Folder 5)
  - Wailuku Honganji Buddhist Temple--Wairuku Honganji Gojikai Riji Senkyo Tohyo Yoshi [Ballot for the election of Board Members of the Association to provide support to the Wailuku Honganji Buddhist Temple], n.d. (Box 151, Folder 6)
- Photographs, 1907-1964; (.25 linear ft.)
  Series consists of one photograph album and small amount of prints.
  - Album, n.d. (Box 151, Folder 7)
  - Reception for Ishii Kikujiro, head of the Commerce Bureau, Ministry of Foreign Affairs in Japan during Meiji period, who visited West Coast, September, 1907 Photo taken in Tacoma, Washington, 1907 September 6 (Box 874, Folder 4)
  - Group photograph, Suto nursery, 1909, 1932, 1953, 1964 (Box 874, Folder 5)
- Printed materials
  - Text book--Methods of intelligent test for the Japanese children in Hawaii, 1925 (Box 151, Folder 8)
    By Kondo Kikujiro, the original title is Hawaii Jido Chinokensa-ho [Intelligence test for Hawaiian children]. In Japanese.
  - Bukkyo gairon [Introduction to Buddhism], 1945 (Box 151, Folder 9)
  - Bukyo no tachiba to Jyodoshinu yosetsu [Principles of Buddhism and introduction to the Jodo Shinshu Sect], 1945 (Box 151, Folder 10)
  - Selected Sunday sermons, 1945 (Box 151, Folder 11)
    Written in Japanese, Sentoku Howa Soka Zuisoroku [A Record of Sermons by the Virtuous Persons of Yore, Flowery Thoughts, and Random Notes]
  - Emergency Service Committee--Final report of the Emergency Service Committee, 1946 (Box 151, Folder 12)
  - Territory of Hawaii Department of Labor and Industrial Relations--Trends and Totals, 1940 (Box 151, Folder 13)
  - Reproduced Japanese calligraphies (Box 874, Folder 6)
  - Reproduced portrait of the emperor of Japan, 1910 (Box 874, Folder 7)
  - Reproduced photographs and pictures of California, Egypt, and Japan, 1913, 1931 (Box 874, Folder 8)
  - Reproduced photographs and pictures of Hawaii (Box 874, Folder 9)
  - Reproduced pictures, n.d. (Box 874, Folder 10)
    Whistler(1834-1903)'s "My Mother" and Kverne(1905-)'s "We"
  - Reproduced pictures mounted on paper, n.d. (Box 874, Folder 11)
    Jan Vermeer's "The Girl with the Red Hat", Winston Homer's "The Wreck", "The Gulf Stream" and "Driftwood", William Davis's "Good Companions", pictures of Bali, Reindel's "New England Harbor" and "Net Menders".
  - Reproduced photographs and pictures mounted on paper (Box 874, Folder 12)
    Animal and sceneries.
  - Newspapers--The Nippu Jiji, The Hawaii Hochi, Special edition for 8th Anniversary for Buddhist Youth Conference, Maui Shinbun, 1935, 1937 (Box 874, Folder 13)